So I'm an artist,
إذاً أنا فنان،
but a little bit of a peculiar one.
و لكني فنان غريب نوعاً ما ،
I don't paint.
أنا لا أدهن.
I can't draw.
ولا أستطيع الرسم.
My shop teacher in high school wrote that I was a menace
كتب عني معلمي في المدرسة الثانوية بأنني خطير
on my report card.
في تقريري الخاص.
You probably don't really want to see my photographs.
ربما لا تود مشاهدة صوري.
But there is one thing I know how to do:
لكن هناك شيء واحد أعرف كيف أفعله:
I know how to program a computer.
أعرف كيف أبرمج الحاسوب.
I can code.
أنا أستطيع أن أبرمج.
And people will tell me that 100 years ago,
سيقول الناس لي أنه قبل 100 عام،
folks like me didn't exist,
شخص مثلي لم يكن موجوداَ،
that it was impossible,
لقد كان مستحيلاَ،
that art made with data is a new thing,
ذلك الفن الذي صُنع من البيانات هو شيء جديد
it's a product of our age,
أنه منتوج عصرنا هذا،
it's something that's really important
أنه لشيء مهم
to think of as something that's very "now."
أن تفكر بشيء بأنه جديد جداَ.
And that's true.
وهذا صحيح.
But there is an art form that's been around for a very long time
ولكن هناك شكل من أشكال الفن كان موجوداَ من فترة طويلة جداَ
that's really about using information,
حول استخدام المعلومات،
abstract information,
المعلومات المجردة،
to make emotionally resonant pieces.
لعمل قطع رنانة عاطفياَ.
And it's called music.
و التي تدعى الموسيقى.
We've been making music for tens of thousands of years, right?
نحن نصنع الموسيقى من عشرات آلاف السنين، صحيح؟
And if you think about what music is --
و إذا تساءلنا ما هي الموسيقى--
notes and chords and keys and harmonies and melodies --
فهي نوتات وحبال ومفاتيح وتجانس والحان --
these things are algorithms.
هذه الأشياء هي خوارزمية.
These things are systems
هذه الأشياء هي أنظمة
that are designed to unfold over time,
تم تصميمها لتتكشف مع مرور الوقت،
to make us feel.
لتجعلنا نشعر بها.
I came to the arts through music.
دخلت الفنون من خلال الموسيقى.
I was trained as a composer,
لقد تدربت كملحن،
and about 15 years ago, I started making pieces
و منذ حوالي 15 عام، بدأت أعمل مقطوعات
that were designed to look at the intersection
تم تصميمها لتبدو في التقاطع
between sound and image,
بين الصوت و الصورة،
to use an image to unveil a musical structure
لتستخدم الصورة لتكشف البنية الموسيقية
or to use a sound to show you something interesting
أو تستخدم الصوت لتظهر شيئاَ مميزاَ
about something that's usually pictorial.
عن شيء عادةَ ما يكون تصويرياَ
So what you're seeing on the screen is literally being drawn
لذلك ما تشاهدوه في الصورة تم رسمه حرفياَ
by the musical structure of the musicians onstage,
بالبنية الموسيقية للموسيقيين على خشبة المسرح،
and there's no accident that it looks like a plant,
وليس مصادفة أنه يبدو كالنبات،
because the underlying algorithmic biology of the plant
لأن علم الأحياء الحسابي الكامن للنبات
is what informed the musical structure in the first place.
ما عرفته أنه بنية موسيقية في المقام الأول.
So once you know how to do this, once you know how to code with media,
لذا بمجرد أن تعرف كيفية القيام بذلك، بمجرد أن تعرف كيف تبرمج بالوسائط،
you can do some pretty cool stuff.
ستتمكن من القيام بأشياء جميلة.
This is a project I did for the Sundance Film Festival.
هذا مشروع أديته في مهرجان صاندانس السينمائي.
Really simple idea: you take every Academy Award Best Picture,
فكرة بسيطة جداَ:ستأخذ أفضل صورة لكل جائزة أكاديمية،
you speed it up to one minute each
تسرع العملية لدقيقة واحدة لكل واحدة
and string them all together.
و تجعلها سلسلة مع بعض.
And so in 75 minutes, I can show you the history of Hollywood cinema.
و بالتالي خلال 75 دقيقة أستطيع أن أطلعك على تاريخ السينما في هوليوود.
And what it really shows you is the history of editing
و ما يظهر لك بالفعل هو تاريخ التحرير
in Hollywood cinema.
في سينما هوليوود.
So on the left, we've got Casablanca; on the right, we've got Chicago.
لذا على اليسار لدينا الدار البيضاء، و على اليمين لدينا شيكاغو.
And you can see that Casablanca is a little easier to read.
و يمكنك مشاهدة أن الدار البيضاء أسهل بقليل للقراءة.
That's because the average length of a cinematic shot in the 1940s
وذلك لأن متوسط طول اللقطات السينمائية في الأربعينات
was 26 seconds,
كان 26 ثانية،
and now it's around six seconds.
و الآن هي حوالي ست ثوان.
This is a project that was inspired
هذا مشروع تم استلهامه
by some work that was funded by the US Federal Government
من عمل تم تمويله من قبل الحكومة الاتحادية الأمريكية
in the early 2000s,
في مطلع الألفينات،
to look at video footage and find a specific actor in any video.
لتمعن في لقطات الفيديو ولتجد ممثلا معينا في أي مقطع.
And so I repurposed this code to train a system on one person
و أعدت توظيف هذا الرمز لتدريب النظام على شخص واحد
in our culture who would never need to be surveilled in that manner,
في ثقافتنا الذي لا يحتاج لمراقبة بهذه الطريقة،
which is Britney Spears.
و التي هي بريتني سبيرز.
I downloaded 2,000 paparazzi photos of Britney Spears
قمت بتحميل 2000 من الصور المأخوذة لبريتني سبيرز
and trained my computer to find her face
و دربت حاسوبي ليجد و يركز على وجهها
and her face alone.
وجهها هي فقط.
I can run any footage of her through it and will center her eyes in the frame,
أستطيع تشغيل أية لقطة لها وسأركز على عينيها في الإطار العام،
and this sort of is a little double commentary
وهذا نوع من التعليق المزدوج
about surveillance in our society.
حول المراقبة في مجتمعنا.
We are very fraught with anxiety about being watched,
نحن قلقون جدا بشأن وجودنا تحت المراقبة،
but then we obsess over celebrity.
و لكن بعد ذلك نصبح مهووسين بالشهرة .
What you're seeing on the screen here is a collaboration I did
ما تشاهدونه في الشاشة هنا هو المشاركة التي قمت بها
with an artist named Lián Amaris.
مع ممثلة تدعى ليان أماريس.
What she did is very simple to explain and describe,
ما قامت به بسيط للغاية للشرح و الوصف،
but very hard to do.
ولكن القيام به صعب جدا.
She took 72 minutes of activity,
التقطت 72 دقيقة من النشاطات،
getting ready for a night out on the town,
واستعدت لليلة خارجا في المدينة،
and stretched it over three days
وامتدت على مدى ثلاثة أيام
and performed it on a traffic island in slow motion in New York City.
و أدتها في جزيرة مكتظة مع نمط حركة بطيء في مدينة نيويورك.
I was there, too, with a film crew.
لقد كنت موجوداَ، أيضاَ مع فريق عمل الفيلم،
We filmed the whole thing,
صورنا كل شيء،
and then we reversed the process, speeding it up to 72 minutes again,
بعد ذلك عكسنا العملية،مع تسريعها إلى 72 دقيقة أيضاَ،
so it looks like she's moving normally
لذلك بدت كأنها تتحرك بشكل طبيعي
and the whole world is flying by.
و العالم كله يحلق بها.
At a certain point, I figured out
و في نقطة معينة،اتضح لي
that what I was doing was making portraits.
أن ما قمت به هو عمل لوحات.
When you think about portraiture, you tend to think about stuff like this.
عندما نفكر في فن التصوير اللوحي، نميل لمثل هكذا أشياء.
The guy on the left is named Gilbert Stuart.
الشاب على اليسار يدعى جيلبرت ستيوارت.
He's sort of the first real portraitist of the United States.
هو أحد أوائل رسامي اللوحات في الولايات المتحدة.
And on the right is his portrait of George Washington from 1796.
و في اليمين اللوحة التي رسمها لجورج واشنطون منذ عام 1796.
This is the so-called Lansdowne portrait.
هذا ما يدعى لوحة لاندس دون.
And if you look at this painting, there's a lot of symbolism, right?
واذا نظرتم الى هذه اللوحة، هناك الكثير من الرمزية، أليس كذلك؟
We've got a rainbow out the window. We've got a sword.
لدينا قوس قزح من النافذة. و لدينا السيف.
We've got a quill on the desk.
و لدينا الريشة على المكتب.
All of these things are meant to evoke
تهدف كل هذه الأشياء لإستحضار
George Washington as the father of the nation.
جورج واشنطن كأب لهذه الأمة.
This is my portrait of George Washington.
وهذه لوحتي لجورج واشنطن.
And this is an eye chart,
و هذا مخطط نظري،
only instead of letters, they're words.
فقط استبدلنا الأحرف بالكلمات.
And what the words are is the 66 words
و الكلمات هي 66 كلمة
in George Washington's State of the Union addresses
في خطابات الاتحاد لجورج واشنطن بشأن الدولة
that he uses more than any other president.
و التي استخدمها أكثر من أي رئيس آخر.
So "gentlemen" has its own symbolism and its own rhetoric.
لذلك "السادة" لها رمزيتها الخاصة و بلاغتها الخاصة.
And it's really kind of significant that that's the word he used the most.
وهذا حقاَ ذو مغزى إستخدامه لهذه الكلمة أكثر من غيرها.
This is the eye chart for George W. Bush,
وهذا المخطط النظري لجورج بوش الثاني:
who was president when I made this piece.
الذي كان رئيسا عندما قدمت هذه الجزء.
And how you get there,
و كيف تحولنا،
from "gentlemen" to "terror" in 43 easy steps,
من " السادة " إلى " الرعب " في 43 خطوة بسيطة،
tells us a lot about American history,
يخبرنا أكثر عن التاريخ الأمريكي،
and gives you a different insight
و يعطينا نظرة مختلفة
than you would have looking at a series of paintings.
أكثر من مجرد النظر بسلسلة من الرسومات.
These pieces provide a history lesson of the United States
هذه القطع تعطينا درساَ في تاريخ الولايات المتحدة
through the political rhetoric of its leaders.
من خلال الخطابات السياسية لقادتها.
Ronald Reagan spent a lot of time talking about deficits.
رونالد ريغان أمضى الكثير من الوقت يتحدث عن العجز.
Bill Clinton spent a lot of time
بيل كلينتون أمضى الكثيرمن الوقت
talking about the century in which he would no longer be president,
يتحدث عن القرن الذي لن يستمر رئيساَ فيه،
but maybe his wife would be.
لكن ربما زوجته ستصبح رئيسة.
Lyndon Johnson was the first President
ليندون جونسون كان الرئيس الأول
to give his State of the Union addresses on prime-time television;
يلقي خطاب حال الدولة في وقت ذروة المشاهدة التلفزيونية;
he began every paragraph with the word "tonight."
بدأ كل مقطع بخطابه بكلمة " الليلة "
And Richard Nixon, or more accurately, his speechwriter,
و ريتشارد نيكسون ،أو بشكل أدق، كاتب خطاباته،
a guy named William Safire,
شاب يدعى ويليام سافير،
spent a lot of time thinking about language
أمضى الكثير من الوقت بالتفكير في اللغة
and making sure that his boss portrayed a rhetoric of honesty.
و التأكد أن رئيسه تفنن في خطاب الصدق
This project is shown as a series of monolithic sculptures.
يظهر هذا المشروع على شكل سلسلة من المنحوتات المتجانسة.
It's an outdoor series of light boxes.
إنها سلسلة خارجية من الصناديق الخفيفة.
And it's important to note that they're to scale,
و من المهم ملاحظة أنهم بنفس النطاق،
so if you stand 20 feet back and you can read between those two black lines,
لذلك إذا وقفت 20 قدماَ للخلف و قرأت ما بين هذه الخطوط السوداء،
you have 20/20 vision.
لديك 20/20 رؤية مختلفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is a portrait. And there's a lot of these.
هذه لوحة فنية و يوجد الكثير من هذا.
There's a lot of ways to do this with data.
و يوجد الكثير من الطرق لعمل هذا الشيء من خلال البيانات و المعلومات.
I started looking for a way
وبدأت أبحث عن وسيلة
to think about how I can do a more democratic form of portraiture,
للتفكير عن كيفية القيام بشكل أكثر ديمقراطية من اللوحات الفنية،
something that's more about my country and how it works.
شيء أكثر حول بلدي، وعن الأمور التي تحدث فيها.
Every 10 years, we make a census in the United States.
كل 10 سنوات، نقوم بإجراء تعداد سكان في الولايات المتحدة.
We literally count people,
نقوم بعد الناس حرفياَ،
find out who lives where, what kind of jobs we've got,
لمعرفة من الذي يعيش و أين، أي نوع من الوظائف لدينا،
the language we speak at home.
اللغات التي نتحدث بها في بلدنا.
And this is important stuff -- really important stuff.
و هذا شيء مهم للغاية.
But it doesn't really tell us who we are.
و لكنه لا يعطينا فكرة كافية عن أنفسنا.
It doesn't tell us about our dreams and our aspirations.
ولا يخبرنا عن أحلامنا و تطلعاتنا.
And so in 2010, I decided to make my own census.
لذلك في عام 2010 قررت أن أقوم بتعدادي الخاص.
And I started looking for a corpus of data
و بدأت بالبحث عن جزء من البيانات
that had a lot of descriptions written by ordinary Americans.
تحتوي العديد من التفاصيل كتبها الأميركيين العاديين.
And it turns out
واتضح لي
that there is such a corpus of data
أن هناك بيانات إحصائية
that's just sitting there for the taking.
جاهزة و مًعدة فقط ليتم أخذها.
It's called online dating.
إنها مواقع التعارف الإلكترونية.
So in 2010, I joined 21 different online dating services,
لذلك في عام 2010 ، أنضممت الى 21 موقع خدمات تعارف مختلف،
as a gay man, a straight man, a gay woman and a straight woman,
كرجل شاذ جنسياَ ، رجل سوي إمرأة شاذة و إمرأة سوية،
in every zip code in America
في كل عنوان بريدي في أمريكا
and downloaded about 19 million people's dating profiles --
و حملت حوالي 19 مليون ملف تعارف شخصي
about 20 percent of the adult population of the United States.
عن حوالي 20 بالمائة من السكان البالغين من الولايات المتحدة.
I have obsessive-compulsive disorder.
بالنسبة لي لدي مرض الوسواس القهري.
This is going to become really freaking obvious. Just go with me.
هذا سيصبح مزعجا بشكل واضح. فقط سايروني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So what I did was I sorted all this stuff by zip code.
قمت بفرز كل هذه البيانات بالعنوان البريدي.
And I looked at word analysis.
و دققت البيانات في مُحلل كلمة.
These are some dating profiles from 2010
هذه بعض ملفات التعارف الشخصي من عام 2010
with the word "lonely" highlighted.
و الممّيزة بكلمة "وحيد"
If you look at these things topographically,
إذا نظرنا لهذه الملفات بشكل طوبوغرافي،
if you imagine dark colors to light colors are more use of the word,
إذا تخيلنا الألوان الداكنة على الألوان الفاتحة
you can see that Appalachia is a pretty lonely place.
يمكنك أن ترى أن أبالاتشيا مكان وحيد جداَ.
You can also see that Nebraska ain't that funny.
يمكنك رؤية أن نبراسكا ليس بالمكان البهيج.
This is the kinky map, so what this is showing you
هذه خريطة غريبة فما يظهر لك من خلالها
is that the women in Alaska need to get together
أن النساء في ألاسكا بحاجة أن يجتمعوا
with the men in southern New Mexico,
مع الرجال في جنوب نيو مكسيكو،
and have a good time.
لقضاء وقت مميز.
And I have this at a pretty granular level,
لدي هذا على مستوى مُفصل جميل جداَ،
so I can tell you that the men in the eastern half of Long Island
لذلك بإمكاني أن أقول أن الرجال في الجزء الشرقي من لونغ ايلاند
are way more interested in being spanked
أكثر استمتاعاَ أن يتم توبيخههم
than men in the western half of Long Island.
أكثر من الرجال في الجزء الغربي من لونغ آيلاند.
This will be your one takeaway from this whole conference.
هذا سيكون لإبعادكم من هذا المؤتمر كله.
You're going to remember that fact for, like, 30 years.
ستبقى هذه الحقيقة عالقة بأذهانكم لمدة تقارب ال30عاماَ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When you bring this down to a cartographic level,
و عندما نتحول من هذا إلى مستوى خرائطي،
you can make maps and do the same trick I was doing with the eye charts.
بإمكانك رسم الخرائط و القيام بنفس الخدعة التي عملتها بالمخططات النظرية.
You've got "pretty." You've got "heartbreak."
ستجد "جذاب." ستجد"غصة."
You've got "gig." You've got "cigarette."
ستجد "عربة." ستجد"سيجارة."
They play in a band and they smoke.
يعزفون في فرقة و يدخنون.
And right above that you can see "email."
وفي الأعلى،ستشاهدون "بريد إلكتروني."
That's Redmond, Washington,
تلك ريدموند، واشنطن،
which is the headquarters of the Microsoft Corporation.
و هي مقر شركة مايكروسوفت.
Some of these you can guess -- so, Los Angeles is "acting"
يمكـّنك توقع بعض من هذا-- لذلك،لوس أنجلوس هي "العمل"
and San Francisco is "gay."
وسان فرانسيسكو "مثلي الجنس".
Some are a little bit more heartbreaking.
و بعضها الآخر أكثر تراجيدية.
In Baton Rouge, they talk about being curvy;
في باتون روج، يتحدثون عن أن تصبح متعرجا;
downstream in New Orleans, they still talk about the flood.
في المصب في نيو أورليانز، لا يزال الحديث عن الفيضانات.
Folks in the American capital will say they're interesting.
الناس في العاصمة الأميركية سيقولون أنهم مثيرون للاهتمام.
People in Baltimore, Maryland, will say they're afraid.
الناس في بالتيمور، ميريلاند، سيقولون أنهم خائفون.
This is New Jersey.
هذه نيو جيرسي.
I grew up somewhere between "annoying" and "cynical."
لقد نشأت في مكان يجمع كونه "مزعجا" و "ساخرا"
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك)(تصفيق)
And New York City's number one word is "now,"
ومدينة نيويورك رقم واحد في العالم "الآن"
as in, "Now I'm working as a waiter, but actually I'm an actor."
حيث أنني" أعمل الآن كنادل، ولكنني فعلياَ ممثل"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or, "Now I'm a professor of engineering at NYU, but actually I'm an artist."
أو " أنني الآن أستاذ الهندسة في جامعة نيويورك، ولكن في الواقع أنا فنان".
If you go upstate, you see "dinosaur."
وإذا ذهبت شمال الولاية،سترى "ديناصور".
That's Syracuse.
تلك هي سيراكيوز.
The best place to eat in Syracuse, New York,
أفضل مكان لتناول الطعام في سيراكيوز، نيويورك،
is a Hell's Angels barbecue joint called Dinosaur Barbecue.
هو مطعم شواء ملائكة الجحيم يدعى مطعم شواء الديناصور.
That's where you would take somebody on a date.
وهو أفضل مكان لمقابلة شخص على موعد.
I live somewhere between "unconditional" and "midsummer," in Midtown Manhattan.
أعيش في مكان"غير خاضع للقواعد" و"متقلب صيفياَ"، وسط مانهاتن.
And this is gentrified North Brooklyn,
وهذه هي الأرستقراطية شمال بروكلين،
so you've got "DJ" and "glamorous" and "hipsters" and "urbane."
هناك سترى "Dj" و"الناس ذوو الجاذبية" و "محبو موسيقى الجاز" و "المدني".
So that's maybe a more democratic portrait.
لهذا هذه لوحة أكثر ديموقراطية.
And the idea was, what if we made red-state and blue-state maps
و كانت الفكرة،ماذا لو عملنا خرائط بولاية حمراء و ولاية زرقاء
based on what we want to do on a Friday night?
بناءَ على ما نريد القيام به في مساء الجمعة؟
This is a self-portrait.
هذه صورة ذاتية.
This is based on my email,
هذه اعتماداَ على بريدي الإلكتروني،
about 500,000 emails sent over 20 years.
من حوالي 500,000 رسالة بريد إلكتروني أرسلتها في 20عاماَ.
You can think of this as a quantified selfie.
يمكنك التفكير في هذه على أنها صورة شخصية كمياَ.
So what I'm doing is running a physics equation
لذلك ما أقوم به هو إجراء معادلة فيزيائية
based on my personal data.
بناءَ على بياناتي الشخصية.
You have to imagine everybody I've ever corresponded with.
يجب أن تتصور كل شخص تقابلت معه.
It started out in the middle and it exploded with a big bang.
بدأت بها في المنتصف وانفجرت مع الانفجار العظيم.
And everybody has gravity to one another,
و كل أحد له أهمية على الآخر،
gravity based on how much they've been emailing,
الأهمية تعتمد على كمية تراسلي معهم إلكترونيا،
who they've been emailing with.
ومن اللذين تراسلت معهم إلكترونياَ،
And it also does sentimental analysis,
و هي تقوم بتحليل شعوري ايضاَ،
so if I say "I love you," you're heavier to me.
لذلك إذا قلت "أحبك" فإذاَ أنت أهم بالنسبة لي.
And you attract to my email addresses in the middle,
و أنت نتجذب لعنوان الإيميل بوسط العناوين،
which act like mainline stars.
و الذي يبدو كالنجوم الرئيسية.
And all the names are handwritten.
وجميع الأسماء مكتوبة بخط اليد.
Sometimes you do this data and this work with real-time data
أحياناَ تقوم بعمل هذه البيانات وهذا العمل كحقائق وقت حقيقي
to illuminate a specific problem in a specific city.
لتسليط الضوء على مشكلة معينة في مدينة معينة.
This is a Walther PPK 9mm semiautomatic handgun
هذا "والذر بي بي ك 9ميليميتر" مسدس شبه أوتوماتيكي
that was used in a shooting in the French Quarter of New Orleans
الذي تم استخدامه في اطلاق نار في الحي الفرنسي في نيو اورليانز
about two years ago on Valentine's Day in an argument over parking.
قبل نحو عامين في عيد الحب في خلاف حول موقف سيارة.
Those are my cigarettes.
تلك هي سجائري.
This is the house where the shooting took place.
هذا هو المنزل الذي تم فيه إطلاق النار.
This project involved a little bit of engineering.
احتوى المشروع على القليل من الجانب الهندسي.
I've got a bike chain rigged up as a cam shaft,
حصلت على سلسلة دراجة تم تركيبها كمحور
with a computer driving it.
يتم قيادتها بكمبيوتر.
That computer and the mechanism are buried in a box.
ذاك الحاسوب و التقنية تم وضعها في صندوق،
The gun's on top welded to a steel plate.
السلاح في المقدمة تم لحمه في لوح صلب.
There's a wire going through to the trigger,
ويوجد سلك ذاهب حتى الزناد،
and the computer in the box is online.
و الحاسوب في الصندوق و متصل بالأنترنت.
It's listening to the 911 feed of the New Orleans Police Department,
إنه يستمع إلى تغذية إذاعة 911 من قسم شرطة نيو اورليانز،
so that anytime there's a shooting reported in New Orleans,
حيث أنه في أي وقت يُضبط إطلاق نار في نيو أورليانز،
(Gunshot sound)
(صوت طلقات الرصاص)
the gun fires.
السلاح يطلق.
Now, there's a blank, so there's no bullet.
الآن،هناك طلقة فارغة، إذاَ لا يوجد رصاص.
There's big light, big noise
يوجد ضوء كبير، ضجة كبيرة
and most importantly, there's a casing.
والأهم من ذلك، هناك تسجيل حالات.
There's about five shootings a day in New Orleans,
حوالي خمسة حالات إطلاق النار في اليوم في نيو اورليانز،
so over the four months this piece was installed,
تم تثبيت هذه القطعة على مدى أربعة أشهر،
the case filled up with bullets.
الصندوق مُليء بوابل من الرصاص.
You guys know what this is -- you call this "data visualization."
أنتم يا شباب تعرفون ماهذا-- يطلق عليه اسم "تصوير البيانات."
When you do it right, it's illuminating.
عندما تقوم به بشكل صحيح، يسلط الضوء.
When you do it wrong, it's anesthetizing.
و عندما تقوم به بشكل خاطئ تقوم بالتخدير.
It reduces people to numbers.
فهو يختزل الناس في أرقام.
So watch out.
لذلك انتبهوا.
One last piece for you.
عينة أخيرة لكم.
I spent the last summer as the artist in residence
قضيت الصيف الماضي كفنان في مسكن
for Times Square.
للتايمز سكوير.
And Times Square in New York is literally the crossroads of the world.
وتايمز سكوير في نيويورك هو حرفيا ملتقى لكل االعالم.
One of the things people don't notice about it
واحد من الاشياء التي لا يلاحظها الناس عنه
is it's the most Instagrammed place on Earth.
أنه المكان الأكثر تواجداَ على إنستاجرام على الأرض.
About every five seconds, someone commits a selfie
في كل خمس ثواني هناك شخص يصور سيلفي له
in Times Square.
في تايمز سكوير.
That's 17,000 a day, and I have them all.
هناك حوالي 17,000 في اليوم، وأنا أملكهم كلهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are some of them with their eyes centered.
و هنا بعض منها مع تركيز على مركز العين.
Every civilization,
كل حضارة،
will use the maximum level of technology available to make art.
سوف تستخدم الحد الأقصى التكنولوجيا المتاحة لخلق فن.
And it's the responsibility of the artist to ask questions
ومسؤولية الفنان هي أن يسأل أسئلة
about what that technology means
حول ما تعني التكنولوجيا.
and how it reflects our culture.
وكيف تنعكس على ثقافتنا.
So I leave you with this: we're more than numbers.
لذا سأترككم مع هذا: نحن أكثر من مجرد أرقام.
We're people, and we have dreams and ideas.
نحن بشر و لدينا أحلام و أفكار.
And reducing us to statistics is something that's done
و تقليصنا لمجرد أحصاءات هو أمرحاصل
at our peril.
يعرضنا للخطر.
Thank you very much.
شكراَ جزيلاَ.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)